Finding Aid for the Ralph Hewins Collected Papers for Biography of J. Paul Getty, circa 1890s-1973, 1984 and undated IA20012
Institutional Records and Archives
Collected papers for biography of J. Paul Getty
Circa 1890s-1973,
1984,
undated
(bulk 1957-1973)
Institutional Records and Archives
Hewins, Ralph
IA20012
2.6 Linear Feet (5 boxes, 1 flat file)
The collection comprises material created or collected by Ralph Hewins in the course of researching and writing the biography The Richest American: J. Paul Getty (1960). The material dates from around the 1890s to 1973 and includes correspondence that discusses Hewins' writings about Getty, a number of unpublished manuscripts, personal photographs given to Hewins by Mr. Getty, and other related photographs, clippings, and ephemera belonging to Hewins.
Related Materials Note
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the people, programs, and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Publications
Hewins, Ralph. The Richest American: J. Paul Getty. New York: Dutton, 1960.
Archival Materials
Getty Institutional Archives
Art and Real Estate Holding Companies Records, 1939-1982 and undated, J. Paul Getty. The Getty Research Institute (IA20011).
J. Paul Getty and the Ashby Sisters Papers, 1926-1992 and undated. The Getty Research Institute (IA20013).
J. Paul Getty Family Papers, circa 1880s-1989 and undated. The Getty Research Institute (IA20009).
J. Paul Getty Diaries, 1938-1946, 1948-1976. The Getty Research Institute (IA40009).
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the Getty by Ralph Hewins in 1984 and subsequently assigned accession number 1986.IA.10.
Restrictions on Access
The records described in accession 1986.IA.10 are available for use by qualified researchers.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection comprises material created or collected by Ralph Hewins in the course of researching and writing the biography The Richest American: J. Paul Getty (1960). The material dates from around the 1890s to 1973 and 1984 and includes correspondence that discusses Hewins' writings about Getty, a number of unpublished manuscripts, personal photographs given to Hewins by Mr. Getty, and other related photographs, clippings, and ephemera belonging to Hewins. The collection has two main strengths: the unpublished material and the photographs.
The papers include a substantial body of correspondence between Hewins and Getty, as well as scattered letters received from Allene Ashby, Penelope Kitson and other Getty family members and associates. The manuscripts comprise Hewins' published and unpublished material about Getty, probably assembled as a potential update to the 1960 biography. These writings are mainly anecdotal in nature; some relate to Getty's friendships and others to his business or recreational activities. A large file of photocopied international clippings chronicle Getty's press coverage through the fifties, sixties and seventies, many of these concerning the kidnapping of Getty's grandson.
The photographic prints and negatives contain over 200 unique images, ranging from approximately the 1890s to the late 1960s, collected by Ralph Hewins. The images include an array of professional photographs and informal snapshots of Getty, his wives, children, friends, associates, businesses, properties, projects, and residences. Some of the images were published in Hewins' book.
Arrangement
These records are organized in three series: Series I. Correspondence, 1957-1971, undated; Series II. Manuscripts and background information, 1960-1973, 1984, undated; Series III. Photographs, circa 1890s-1960s.
Biography
Ralph Hewins (d. 1984) was a professional journalist largely concerned with the very wealthy. He was the author of The Richest American: J. Paul Getty (1960). Hewins became a personal friend of Mr. Getty during the years he spent researching and writing Getty's biography.
Billionaires -- United States -- 20th century; Clippings (information artifacts); Art objects -- Collectors and collecting; Manuscripts; Correspondence; Photographic prints; Ephemera; Hewins, Ralph; Kitson, Penelope; Getty, J. Paul (Jean Paul), 1892-1976; Ashby, Allene
- Correspondence, 1957-1971; undated; Series I.; 0.1 Linear Feet (1 box)
  Arrangement
  These records are arranged in general chronological order.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records consist of correspondence, primarily to and from Ralph Hewins, a biographer and acquaintance of J. Paul Getty, 1957-1971 and undated. This correspondence largely relates to Hewins' writings on Getty, and includes correspondence with Getty and other individuals, including Maxwell Balfour, president of Getty's Spartan Aircraft Company. The letters discuss the publication of Hewins' 1960 biography of Getty, The Richest American, as well as personal events in Hewins' life related to his work on the biography.
  See also Series III. Photographs, for related photographs.
  - Correspondence, 1957-1966; undated; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 3-4)
  - J. Paul Getty cards to Hewins, 1961-1968; undated (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 5)
- Manuscripts and background information, 1959-1973; 1984,; undated; Series II.; 2 Linear Feet (3 boxes, 1 flat file)
  These records are generally arranged in the order of accession. The larger manuscripts have been grouped together.
  Records consist of typescript manuscripts, clippings, ephemera, and photographs, 1960-1973, 1984, and undated, written and collected by Ralph Hewins about J. Paul Getty and comprising Hewins' published and unpublished material about Getty. Some of the material seems to have been assembled as an update to his book, The Richest American: J. Paul Getty (New York: 1960). The manuscripts are a set of short articles and two versions of the manuscript for The Zillionaire: Getty at 80 (unpublished); these contain Hewins' edits. The short works are anecdotal in nature; some relate to Getty's friendships and others to his business or recreational activities. The ephemera consists of cards, invitations and announcements relating to Getty and his companies.
  - "The Zillionaire: Getty at 80, Part I: The Man," edited manuscript, 1971; [4 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 6-9)
  - "Getty at 80, Part II: The Businessman," edited manuscript, 1971; [4 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 10-13)
  - "Getty at 80, Part III: The Whole Man," edited manuscript, 1971 (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 14)
  - "Getty at 80," Hewins' notes and edits, 1971; [2 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 15-16)
  - The Zillionaire: early draft, undated; [1-2 of 5 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-1, Folder 17-18)
  - The Zillionaire: early draft, undated; [3-5 of 5 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous notes, manuscript pages, 1959-1960; 1963,; 1966,; 1973 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 4)
  - "The Mystery Wife of J. Paul Getty,", 1960 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 5)
  - "Getty's 'Mystery House,'", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 6)
  - "The World's Richest Sportsman: J. Paul Getty,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 7)
  - "Mr. Getty to fly again,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 8)
  - "Mr. Getty economises,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 9)
  - "Mr. Getty's iron bars,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 10)
  - "A Murder Shakes the Arabian Oilfields,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 11)
  - "Rival Books About Paul Getty,", 1973 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 12)
  - "Mrs. Kitson's treat,", 1960 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 13)
  - "Mr. Getty's quick return,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 14)
  - "Tanker Sickness,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 15)
  - "Why I'm the Richest,", 1961 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 16)
  - "The New Mr. Getty," and letter, 1961 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 17)
  - "What I Think of Howard Hughes,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 18)
  - Hewins letter to editor, London Daily Telegraph, re: Howard Hughes, undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 19)
  - "The Unknown Giant,", undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 20)
  - Hewins' notes and notebook, undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 21)
  - Notes, clippings, card from George Getty, 1971-1972 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 22)
  - Getty-related ephemera collected by Hewins, 1960-1961; 1966,; 1970 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 23)
  - Papers found in autographed copy of "How to be Rich" with dedication, 1962-1971 (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 24)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 25)
  - Hewins' clippings file, undated; [5 files] (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 26-30)
  - Clippings (photocopies), ephemera, 1984; undated (Box 1986.IA.10-2, Folder 31)
  - Program for ceremony conferring honorary law degree to J. Paul Getty from Ohio Northern University, August 21, 1966 (Box 1986.IA.10-5)
  - "Herculaneum and the Villa of the Papyri," Instituto Geographico de Agostini, 1963 (Box 1986.IA.10-5)
  - "J. Paul Getty's Worldwide Empire" map, undated (Flatfile 1986.IA.10-6)
- Photographs, circa 1890s-1960s; and undated; Series III.; 0.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
  The photographs have been roughly arranged by subject. Within each subject the images are arranged numerically accoring to the creator's original numbering system (some prints have numbers written in pencil on the verso). Some of the photographic prints are accompanied by negatives, which are housed in neighboring sleeves.
  Materials consist of over 200 photographic prints and negatives, ranging from around the 1890s to the late 1960s, collected by Ralph Hewins, depicting J. Paul Getty, family, friends, business associates, properties, and a reception for Hewins' book The Richest American: J. Paul Getty (1960). The records also include photocopies of all photographs. Some of the photographs were published in Hewins' book. The vast majority of the photographs are black-and-white.
  See also Series I. Correspondence, for related items.
  - J. Paul Getty, 1890s-1960s; (approximately 42 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Scope and Contents
    Material comprises formal portraits and casual snapshots featuring J. Paul Getty, including photographs of him as a child, with family, with a couple of his wives, with friends, with business associates, with his Spartan aircraft staff, with English Queen Elizabeth the Queen Mother, and with his lion cub. Material also includes shots of Getty receiving the Legion of Honor, receiving an honorary academic degree, standing in oil fields, standing on deck the tanker "George F. Getty," and visiting archaeological sites. All but one of the photos is in black-and-white.
  - Getty family and family history, circa 1890-1960s; (approximately 23 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material comprises images of J. Paul Getty's parents, George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty; sister, Gertrude Lois Getty; wives, Jeannette McDermot, Allene Ashby, Ann Rork, Fini Helmly; children, Eugene Paul Getty II, Gordon Getty, George F. Getty, and Timmy Getty; and young grandchildren, Anne, Caroline, Claire, and J. Paul Getty III. Photos of wife, Teddy are located with the photos of J. Paul Getty. Photos of Ronald Getty are located with Ralph Hewins' book signing images. Persons listed above may also appear in images of various events listed below. Images are black-and-white except for one hand-tinted photograph of Allene Ashby.
  - Getty residences, 1908; and undated; (12 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material comprises images of Getty residences: South Kingsley Drive (Los Angeles); Sutton Place (England); exterior of the Getty Ranch House (near Malibu, California) and its zoo; and La Posta Vecchia (Gaeta, Italy).
  - People, circa 1950s and 1960s; (approximately 12 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material includes photographs of Ralph Hewins, Penelope Kitson, President Eisenhower, and others.
  - Museum gallery and art objects, undated; (3 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Materials include images of a museum gallery within the Getty Ranch House, the "Ardibil Carpet," and the "Medalllion and Tree Carpet."
  - Business: Japan, 1965; and undated; (approximately 20 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material includes images of Japanese business associates, an oil tanker, Ralph Hewins, and others.
  - Business: Spartan, circa 1940s; (7 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material includes an aerial view of the Spartan facility, and Spartan mobile home interiors, William F. Humphry, Maxwell W. Balfour, and British Royal Air Force (RAF) student pilots at the Spartan School of Aeronautics. See also images of J. Paul Getty for an additional photograph of Spartan employees.
  - Business: various, circa 1930s-1960s; (approximately 82 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material comprises exterior shots of various Getty buildings and models of buildings; refineries; filling station; interior of the Cotillion Room (Hotel Pierre, NY); aerial view of Hotel Pierre Marques (Alcapulco); and oil tankers, derricks, drilling sites, pipelines, employees and other shots related to the petroleum business.
  - Hotel Pierre event, March 1960; (26 8 x 10"; 27 3 x 5"; and 2 3 x 5" color) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Materials comprise professional photographs stamped "Hotel Pierre Public Relations, Fifth Ave. & 61st Street, New York, N.Y." and "Please credit Irwin Dribben, New York" on verso. Photographs feature Ralph Hewins, George F. Getty II, and Gloria Getty.
  - Hewins' book signing, 1960; (approximately 18 images) (Box 1986.IA.10-4)
    Material documents a reception held at the J. Paul Getty Museum (galleries and courtyard of the Ranch House) to commemorate the publication of Ralph Hewins' biography of J. Paul Getty. Material includes images of Ralph Hewins; George F. Getty II and his wife, Gloria Getty; Ronald Getty, and his mother, Fini Helmle; and others.
  - Annotated photocopies of prints in the collection, undated (Box 1986.IA.10-3, Folder 1-7)